Guide to the Oregon State University Military Photographs Collection 1875-1975
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
Oregon State University Military Photographs Collection
1875-1975
1915-1965
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center Special Collections & Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu
P 002
2 cubic feet, including 1000 photographs 13 boxes, including 4 oversize boxes, and 2 map folders
The Oregon State University Military Photographs Collection consists of images of military education and cadets at Oregon State from various sources and time periods. Individual images include portraits and group shots of military cadets and officers, as well as reviews, formations, training, and instructional materials. Photographs are arranged chronologically by historical era. Courses in military science have been taught at Oregon State since the early 1870s.
Historical Note:
Courses in Military Science and Tactics were first taught at Oregon State in 1872. In 1873 Captain Benjamin D. Boswell was appointed Professor of Military Science and Tactics (1873-1876), the first U.S. Army officer on active duty to hold such a position in any land grant college in the West. The first cadet uniforms, worn at all times by male students, were gray with caps of the Civil War type. The more familiar blue uniforms were adopted in 1893.
ROTC at Oregon State University is made up of the Departments of Military Science, Naval Science, and Air Force Studies. In 1917, the Department of Military Sciences became responsible for all military training under the National Defense Act of 1916. The act expanded and standardized the training of Army Officers by colleges and universities and established the Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC). During World War II, OSU became known as the "West Point of the West" for commissioning more officers than any other non-military academy in the nation. At the end of World War II, the Secretary of the Navy commissioned the Department of Naval Science (ROTC) on this campus to provide the training of both Navy and Marine Corps officers. On July 1, 1949, the U.S. Air Force activated an AFROTC unit that is now called the Department of Air Force Studies. As of 1999, OSU is one of only 48 colleges and universities that offers education for all three military departments.
Originally, two years of military science and tactics were required of all able-bodied male students, but since 1962, ROTC has been voluntary. Since 1965, two-year programs have been available for students who have finished two years of college but have not taken ROTC previously.
The Oregon State University Military Photographs Collection contains images of Oregon State military science and tactics cadets and officers from its beginning in 1873 through the 1960s. Many photographs are prints of images found in Oregon State publications such as the Beaver yearbook, Oregon Stater alumni magazine and the Barometer campus newspaper. The development of cadet uniforms and training can be seen throughout the collection. Images include views of campus buildings and locations during various eras. The collection contains prints and original negatives, glass negatives/positives (some hand colored), and instructional lantern slides of World War I vintage.
Subject matter features cadet formations on parade fields during military inspection day events, artillery, cavalry and engineering training scenes and casual snapshots. The collection includes a large group of glass negatives of early Oregon Agricultural College cadet corps circa 1870 through 1918. A glass lantern slide collection of instructional materials for Military Tactics courses includes images from World War One, with a focus on combat engineers. Numerous images of Ulysses Grant McAlexander are included in the collection. After WWI, the Oregon Agricultural College ROTC program expanded to include the new mechanized units developed in the Great War. Photographs from this period show the new cadet artillery batteries equipped with surplus US Army equipment. The annual inspection of cadets by dignitaries was a popular event during the college year and is well documented in the collection. Dignitaries that are depicted include Oregon Governors Charles Martin and Charles Sprague and Oregon State Presidents William Jasper Kerr, George Peavy, and A.L. Strand. The US Army ROTC Pershing Rifles are well represented with photographs of drill team competitions and awards during the 1960s. Stock U.S. Military photographs and college photographs from all eras are found in the series.
Collection is open for research.
The Oregon State University Military Photographs Collection is arranged into five series by chronological era: I. Pre World War One, 1875-1917; II. World War One, 1916-1918; III. Inter-War Years, 1919-1939; IV. World War Two, 1940-1945; V. Cold War Years, 1946-1975. The series include subseries; photographs are arranged numerically within subseries and series.
The materials were acquired from a variety of donors from the 1960s through 1990s.
Photographs of military cadets and their activities are found in many collections. Harriet's Collection (P HC) has prints made from the glass negatives in P 002 and other original images. Various military records and photographs are found in the following collections: Ulysses Grant McAlexander Collection; Army ROTC Photographs (P 257), Reserve Officer Training Corps (ROTC) Records (RG 058), Army Specialized Training Program Records (RG 059); Student Army Training Corps Records (RG 060); and Air Force ROTC Photographs (P 281).
Kerr, William Jasper, 1863-1947.; Martin, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1863-1946.; McAlexander, Ulysses Grant, 1864-1936.; Peavy, George Wilcox, 1869-1951.; Sprague, Charles A. (Charles Arthur), 1887-1969.; Strand, A. L. (August Leroy), 1894-
Army Specialized Training Program (U.S.); Oregon Agricultural College. Cadet Corps.; Oregon Agricultural College--Students.; Oregon State College--Students.; Oregon State University. Dept. of Air Force Studies.; Oregon State University. Dept. of Military Science.; Oregon State University--Students.; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps.; United States. Air Force ROTC.; United States. Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps.; United States. Army. Students’ Army Training Corps.
Military education--Oregon--Corvallis.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Schools.; World War, 1939-1945--War work--Schools.
Fort Lewis (Wash.)
Film negatives.; Glass negatives.; Lantern slides.; Panoramic photographs.; Photographic prints.; Photographic postcards.; Slides.
Colleges and Universities; Military; Student Life; Oregon; Washington (State); Corvallis; Photographs
- Pre World War One, 1875-1917; Series I
  Photographs of OAC Cadets dating from 1875 up to 1917. Uniforms and weapons in transition are indicated in series. Campus buildings in background are of special note. US Army training Staff in photographs. Series includes prints and glass negatives of photographs appearing in various OAC publications.
  - Pre WWI Glass Negatives, 1900-1917
    Sub-series contains glass negatives and positives of OAC Cadets and OAC Band during the period prior to U.S. entry into World War One. Many of the negatives have been reproduced in period publications. Copies of photographs from these negatives are found elsewhere in collection.
    - OAC Cadet Band in front of Education Hall, circa 1915; P002:357; 11X14 glass negative (Box 5)
      Military Band in front of Education Hall (then Agriculture Hall) in 1915. The OAC Cadet Band is shown with instruments wearing the brimmed caps and canvas puttees of the 1910-1917 period. Good detail of facade of Education Hall. Ball Studio Photo, copy write 1915 does not show up on this glass plate. Also of note is a man standing to the far left of photo, he is not seen in any other prints or negatives of this image (This image has been reprinted and in various sizes throughout many OSU photo collections)
      Stored in Oversize Glass Negative Box #5
    - Cadet formations on inspection day, circa 1910; P002:358; 11X14 glass negative (Box 5)
      Formation of a cadet companies in review. Possibly a photograph used in OAC publication such as Orange Yearbook or Oregon Stater. Uniforms are of the 1902-1908 pattern including canvas leggings and 1902 brimmed service caps. Of note is the elaborate corded lanyards as part of uniform, not found in other period scenes. Uniforms of this type were transitional between the old blue style and the change to WWI khaki.
      Stored in Large Glass Negative Box #5
    - Cadet formations with Education and Benton Hall in background, circa 1910; P002:359; 11X14 glass negative (Box 5)
      Military review day. Formation of cadets to the left of wide view photo is difficult to see detail. Automobile by cadets (possibly delivering dignitaries) is of circa 1915 vintage. Education Hall (Then Ag Hall) in background, Benton Hall is seen behind trees. Original Armory (Women's Gymnasium) is visible behind Education Hall. Group of spectators to the right of photograph indicates this event was probably the annual review of Cadet Corps by Military Department.
    - Cadets forming "OAC" on parade field, circa 1910; P002:360; 11X14 glass negative (Box 5)
      Large glass negative of the much used "OAC formation of cadets". Used first in the 1910-1911 OAC Catalog, the photo also shows up in the 1910 Orange Yearbook. The uniforms and instruments of the OAC band are in excellent detail. Houses and streets are in clear focus, showing fence lines and outhouses.
    - OAC basketball team "Oregon Champs" 1911, circa 1911; P002:361; 11X14 glass negative (Box 5)
      OAC Basketball team posed with seated coach. The team is holding a basketball with "Oregon Champs" written on it. A small child is standing with the coach wearing a uniform shirt with "O" on it.
    - Cadets in formation by Agriculture Building, circa 1910; P002:363; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Columns of OAC Cadet officers and companies on path adjacent to Agriculture building (now Strand Ag Building). Uniforms are Olive Drab tunics with canvas puttees and brimmed caps. Good detail of Ag building facade and housing in background.
    - Cadets in prone position with rifles, circa 1910; P002:364; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Line of cadets laying in prone position with rifles, cadet officers with sabres behind. Location on campus is listed as "mid campus", circa 1910. Uniforms are Pre WWI with the brimmed caps and canvas puttees. Olive drab tunics on all cadets. Rifles are Krag-Jorgensen .30 of Spanish American War vintage. It is unclear whether this is a staged photograph or actual firing practice.
    - Cadet Formation, circa 1910; P002:365; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Formation of cadets and officers on lower campus (mid campus?) looking east. Court house and Congregational Church in background. Olive Drab uniforms with brimmed caps and canvas puttees.
    - Cadet company standing with rifles aimed, circa 1910; P002:366; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Cadet Company in formation with rifles at shoulders aimed. Probably lower campus with large trees in background. Olive drab uniforms with brimmed caps and canvas puttees. Cadets have bayonet scabbards on their web belts. Rifles are the Spanish American War vintage Krag-Jorgenson bolt action .30 caliber.
    - Cadets in prone position with rifles, circa 1910; P002:367; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Similar view to P002:364, a formation of cadets in line with rifles ready. Prone position firing and kneeling spotters behind formation. Campus location is listed as lower campus on this photo. Good detail of houses in background. Period uniforms dates scene to circa 1910.
    - Cadet Review lower campus, circa 1905; P002:371; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Glass Positive, hand colored. Cadets in formation for review in parade field, lower campus. Agriculture Hall (Later Education Hall) in background. Benton Hall visible. A ditch with wood plank bridge is in foreground, found on other negatives in this series. Dating is after 1902 but before 1915 based on buildings and uniforms visible. Hand coloring is of note on this artifact.
    - Spectators at Military Tournament, Cadet Officer viewing, circa 1910; P002:372; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Group of spectators with cadet officer in foreground. Original description lists Dr. Kerr in group, which is possible, but unconfirmed. Good detail of period clothing of civilians. Cadet officer is wearing brimmed cap with leather puttees. The leather puttees were issued to cavalry officers primarily.
    - Cadets demonstrating medic techniques, P002:373; 6.5X8.5 glass negative (Box 6)
      Cadets demonstrating medical techniques, stretcher bearers, two man carry. Uniforms date photo to late 1880s to 1900. Standard forage caps are worn, blue uniforms with large chevrons and striped pants. Medical corps training was part of the Military curriculum during this period, with a dedicated medical unit training coming after the turn of the century. Building in background is undetermined, but style of stonework can be used for identification. Possibly could be the 1902 Agriculture Hall facade.
    - OAC Cadet Band in front of Education Hall 1915, P002:374; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Military Band in front of Education Hall (then Agriculture Hall) in 1915. The OAC Cadet Band is shown with instruments wearing the brimmed caps and canvas puttees of the 1910-1917 period. Good detail of facade of Education Hall. Ball Studio Photo, copy write 1915.
    - Cadets in formation for review, Ag Hall in background, circa 1910; P002:375; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Same view as the hand colored P002.371. Closer view, still showing bridge over ditch. Cadets in formation for review in parade field, lower campus. Agriculture Hall (Later Education Hall) in background. Benton Hall visible. A ditch with wood plank bridge is in foreground, found on other negatives in this series. Dating is after 1902 but before 1915 based on buildings and uniforms visible.
    - OAC Cadet squad with Company F flags, circa 1910; P002:376; 8X10 glass positive (Box 6)
      Good detail shot of cadet uniforms of the pre-WWI olive drab period. Brim caps and canvas puttees. Photo shows Company F guidon flags. Cadet officers with sabres. Houses on Monroe(?) in background.
    - Cadets drilling inside Armory, circa 1915; P002:377; 8X10 glass negative (Box 6)
      Interior shot of armory, built in 1911. Uniforms of cadets indicate the circa 1915 period with brim caps. Good detail of structure in parade area of Armory.
    - Cadet formations on lower campus by Benton Hall, circa 1905; P002:378; 8X10 glass negative (Box 6)
      Broad panoramic view of lower campus parade field. Formations of cadets in distance with Benton Hall to the side. Difficult to date photo based on uniforms due to lack of detail. Benton Hall possibly still in original brick (before 1899 stucco refurbishment) but detail is small. Circa date of turn of the century to early 1910s based on buildings visible in scene.
    - Cadet review, lower campus, Education Hall in background, circa 1915; P002:379; 8X10 glass negative (Box 6)
    - OAC Cadet Band by Education Hall, circa 1912; P002:380; 8X10 glass negative (Box 6)
      Detailed photograph of OAC Cadet Band, posed in two rows with instruments. Background of Education Hall is confirmed by arches and details. The OAC Cadet Band bass drum is posed to the right of group. The photo is not marked Ball Studio but is of the same vintage as others in collection. Early dating of the photo is based on brimmed caps and canvas puttees of uniforms.
    - Cadet Company standing with rifles, circa 1910; P002:381; 8X10 glass negative (Box 6)
      Negative version of P002:366. Cadet Company in formation with rifles at shoulders aimed. Probably lower campus with large trees in background. Olive drab uniforms with brimmed caps and canvas puttees. Cadets have bayonet scabbards on their web belts. Rifles are the Spanish American War vintage Krag-Jorgenson bolt action .30 caliber.
    - Studio group portrait OAC Cadet officers, circa 1900, circa 1895; P002:382; 8X10 glass negative (Box 6)
      Negative version of P002:400. Posed photograph in front of backdrop of OAC Officer Cadets. Identification of subjects based on "Alumni Files", with dating of 1898-1902 and a received date of 1960. The uniforms are of the circa 1900 vintage, including high collars and older style campaign hats. The print version has identification of subjects written in pen on reverse has been edited in red pencil. "Standing 1- (Blank), 2- Dr. Berges, 3. John Edwards 1902 class, 4 - (Blank), Sitting: 1- Alfred Saunders (Jake), 2- Grant Elgin. Note written later: #3, Standing, also identified as Major Frank Edwards, Dec. 1914."
    - OAC cadets in box formation with rifles at ready, circa 1895; P002:383; 8X10 glass negative (Box 6)
      Negative version of print in collection P002:383. OAC Cadet "Battalion" in box formation on parade field with rifles, dated May 1895. The caption on the most original of the prints states, "OAC Cadet Battalion - May 1895 Strut Column". The box formation shown can be dated back to Napoleonic Tactics (adaptation of ancient warfare formations). Still practiced in the late 19th to early 20th century infantry training. Uniforms are of the pattern 1892 sack coats with a variety of Forage Caps shown in the group. Most of the cadets are wearing the 1895 Forage cap, which was patterned after the contemporary caps worn by firemen and train conductors, and did not find favor with the troops. There are still a few cadets with the Civil War era looking Forage Cap pattern 1872. Rifles issued to the cadets were most probably the M1884 Rifle, .45 Caliber with the Buffington Rear Sight. Buildings in the background are notable, showing the carriage house and Mechanical Hall with the railroad spur (Corvallis and Eastern RR) still in place.
    - Cadets with Band in formation by Benton Hall(Related to P002:177), circa 1895; P002:384; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Negative version of print P002:177. Good detail photograph of cadets in formation on lower campus by administration building. Photograph is described on reverse as being 1898, notes about admin building steps. Original brick facade of Benton Hall is visible before the 1899 stucco refurbishing. Listed as page 159A, unknown publication. Cadets are in dress uniforms, showing large stripes on sleeves. OAC cadet band leading formation.
    - Cadet officers with sabres in line by Benton Hall, circa 1900; P002:385; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Line of cadet officers at parade rest with sabres. Columns of Benton Hall in background, stucco wall finish dates photo to after 1899. The uniforms in photo are of the pre-1908 style with soft campaign hat designs. Belted tunics with unexposed buttons. Possibly on graduation day waiting for commissioning.
    - OAC Cadets drilling on lower campus - rifles over heads, circa 1910; P002:386; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Negative version of photo P002:386 (duplicate #) in series. OAC Cadets drilling on field on lower campus. Benton hall in background, water tank and smokestack of power plant (now Owens hall) behind. Good detail of Education Hall to the left of photo. Men are drilling with rifles held overhead, lead by Cadet officer with sabre.
    - OAC Cadet officers posing in dress uniform, circa 1905; P002:387; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      OAC Cadet officers posing in rank with dress uniforms and sabres. Early 1900s uniform style with soft campaign hats and tunics with unexposed buttons. Cadets are possibly same group as P002:385. Photo is posed probably on lower campus by Benton Hall. Larger trees in background are visible in many period photographs of this area.
    - Cadet corps in formation, east of old Armory, circa 1905; P002:388; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Formation of OAC Cadets in dress uniforms (Inspection day?). Old Armory (Women's Gym) in background. Good detail of buildings. Uniforms are of the turn of the century style with covered buttons and soft campaign hats. Officers with sabres, cadets in company formation with rifles.
    - Cadet formation next to Administration Building (Benton Hall), circa 1895; P002:389; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Cadet formation at attention for inspection, circa 1895. Uniforms include forage caps of civil war style, large chevron stripes on sleeves. Cadets have older style Springfield Armory rifles with fixed bayonets. Of significant note with this image is the detail of Administration Building (now Benton Hall). Excellent detail of old east steps, no hands on clock and roof details. Clock tower has wrought iron(?) details on peak, possible lightning rod is visible. Further study of the details is warranted.
    - Cadet formations in review, lower campus, Jefferson Street buildings visible, circa 1910; P002:390; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      OAC Cadet companies on parade field during military review. Good detail of houses and churches on Jefferson Street in background. Uniforms are of the Pre WWI vintage with brimmed caps and puttees.
    - Cadet formation on lower campus, Benton Hall in background, circa 1905; P002:392; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Cadets in review formation on lower campus with Benton Hall and windmills in background. Uniforms indicate Pre 1910 style with brimmed caps and high boots. Cadet officers with sabres. Company colors are in formation. Clock face painted on Benton Hall, brick facade.
    - Cadet officers in dress uniforms posing with artillery piece, circa 1900; P002:393; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Cadet officers in dress uniforms and sabres posing with early artillery piece. The muzzle loading cannons were replaced with more modern breech loaders after the turn of the century. Cadet uniforms include tunics with covered buttons, soft campaign hats and belts with square buckles. One cadet is holding a band instrument. Probably located on lower campus next to tree line. Uniforms indicate Spanish American war period.
    - Cadets on lower campus, Benton, Education Halls visible, circa 1902; P002:395; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Cadet formation in review on lower campus parade field. Benton Hall and Education Hall (Then known as Science Building, built in 1902) visible. Detail of cadets is too small to determine uniforms, but the formation appears to be the same as P002:392 circa 1905. Building details in background on this image are clear and can be used in dating scene.
    - Cadets in Company formation on lower campus, circa 1905; P002:396; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Cadets in company formations with cadet band leading. View looking east toward the city of Corvallis, Jefferson Street in foreground. Uniforms indicate circa 1905 vintage with brimmed caps. Full contingent of OAC Cadets shown in this view, probably Military Review day.
    - Probably same view as P002:371, Cadet formation on lower campus, circa 1902; P002:397; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
    - Signal Corps Cadets posed in dress uniforms, circa 1900; P002:398; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)
      Cadets posed close to building (possibly Benton Hall) in dress uniforms, circa 1900. The emblems on the sleeves indicate US Army Signal Corps. The cadets are holding the company guidon colors. Uniforms include soft campaign hats and tunics with belts.
    - Cadet Officers portrait studio image, circa 1900; P002:400; 8X10 glass negative (Box 7)